# 你看 這個鯉魚喲
Look! These carps,
# 很漂亮的哦 這個紅色的鯉魚
are really pretty, the red carps.
# 兄弟以前 兄弟前幾天
My buddy, few, a few days ago,
# 放
drained
# 把他 他自己的魚塘啊
drained all the water, from his, his pond,
# 把水放乾啦
a few days ago.
# 抓了這紅鯉魚 全部送到我這裡來
He then caught the red carps and sent them all to me.
# 我也不知道他怎麼了
Who knows what's happened to him.
# 我說我很喜歡紅色的 他就送給我啦
He said that I would like the red ones. And then he gave me all.
# 放到我們這個池塘里面去
Let me put them into our pond.
# 你看 這個都是鯉魚來的
Look! These are all carps.
# 都是大肚子的 (註︰估計是說懷孕)
And they are all pregnant.
# 你看 肚子好大
Look! The belly is so big.
# 放到我們這小池裡面去
Let's put it into our small pond here.
# 以後你就是我們家的啊
From now on, you are part of our family.
# 跟我們 姓劉
You name is now Liu, the same as us,
# 跟我姓劉
the same as me.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 拍得我一身水
You make me wet.
# 好 把好放乾一點
Alright! Let me pour some water away.
# 你看
Look!
# 下去
Get into the pond!
# 早生貴子
I wish you a big family.
# 多生點蛋
Lay more eggs!
# 嗯 這肚子好大
Um! This one has a very big belly.
# 是啊 這魚快
Ya! The fish is about to,
# 這個 這個魚都快生啦
the, the fish is about to give birth.
# 放到這裡
Put it here,
# 讓它 繁殖出來好多小
so that it can breed a lot of small,
# 小 小鯉魚出來
small, small carps.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個也是大肚子的
This is also pregnant.
# 這個肯定是公的 這個
And this one must be male, this one.
# 這個 這個是公的
This one, this is male.
# 一家人
The whole family,
# 就在這池子裡面養著哦
will be living in this pond.
# 不要打架
Don't fight!
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 這水都颷出來啦
The water is splashing out!
# 相親相愛
Love each other!
# 和諧相處
Live in harmony!
# 好啦
Alright!
# 讓他們
Let them,
# 放在這裡養
stay here.
# 有公的也有母的
There are males and females.
# 它們
They,
# 它們肯定會到春天的時候
they will certainly lay eggs,
# 會下蛋的
when spring comes.
# 會下小魚
They will give birth to small fish.
# 啊 那個水 也接好啦
Ah! The water, is alright now.
# 這個水是從出山上引
The water is caught from the,
# 這個水是從山上引下來的
the water is caught from the hill.
# 今天又來兄弟家摘點杮子啊
Today I come to my buddy's place to pick some persimmons again.
# 現在杮子都透了
The persimmons are now all ready.
# 再不摘的話就會壞掉
They will be rotten if they are left in the trees.
# 哇! 大狼狗
Wa! Big wolf-dog!
# 叫都不敢叫
It doesn't even dare to make a sound.
# 你看 我這個兄弟家 家大業大的
Look! This buddy, this buddy is running a large business.
# 這個是一個農莊來的哦
This place is a grange.
# 杮子樹
Persimmon trees!
# 好多啊
Really a lot!
# 這要站到樓頂上去才好搞
It would be much easier on the rooftop.
# 我去找個 找個樓梯上樓頂
Let me find, find the staircase to the rooftop.
# 你看 兄弟那個 上頂上的樓梯都沒有啦
Look! My buddy, my buddy doesn't even have a staircase to the rooftop.
# 還是上樹吧
I'd better climb the tree.
# 看一下好不好吃
Let me see if it tastes good.
# 已經捽扁了
It's already crushed.
# 好甜啊
It's so sweet!
# 這個好好吃哦
It tastes really good!
# 現在打了霜
It has been frosted.
# 好甜啊現在
And it's so sweet now.
# 樹上還有好多啊
There are still a lot in the tree.
# 再摘一點 摘太少了
Let me pick more, it's too few.
# 這棵太高啦 要爬樹的
The tree is simply too tall. I need to climb it.
# 再站在樹底下 都上不去
There's no way to climb onto the tree by staying under it.
# 在上面來接
You catch down there.
# 哇 這樣不安全哦
Wa! It's not safe!
# 攝影小哥 把你的那個皮帶給我
Mr. Cameraman! Give me your belt!
# 要不然會那個的 會掉下去的 安全一點
Otherwise I will, you know, I will drop. Better safe than sorry.
# 等下 扔
Wait! Throw!
# 好
Alright!
# 啊 這樣就安全啦
Ah! It's safe now.
# 肯定要兩個人接 一個人接 全爆了
You need both of you. All would be crushed if there's only one catching.
# 弟弟老是接不住 沒辦法
Our brothers can never get any. Well...
# 算啦
Let's give up.
# 還是留給鳥吃吧
The rest are better left for the birds.
# 掉 掉下來摔破了 太浪費
It would be too much a waste if, if they are all crushed.
# 你看 這個 最黃的
Look! This is, the most golden yellow.
# 我把它掰開吃了
Let me crack it open and eat it.
# 現不還是很 不是很熟
It's not still, it's still not too ready.
# 不過現在打了霜 很甜
But it's very sweet as it has been frosted.
# 這種杮子
These persimmons,
# 就這樣吃可以吃啦
can be just eaten right away.
# 沒打霜之前就有點苦澀
It would taste a bit bitter if it has not been frosted.
# 現在還好
But it's not too bad now.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
The video ends here.
# 回家
Let's go!